The Mr. and Mrs. Henry Dain Papers
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
The Mr. and Mrs. Henry Dain Papers
1963 - 1967
Henry Dain; Mrs. Henry Dain
NPKMC-212-162>
3.5 Linear Feet
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
The Mr. and Mrs. Henry Dain Papers contains documents and clipping related to the Hudson River Environmental Society, underground transmission lines, and the proposed Cornwall Storage Pump.
Acquisitions Information
The Mr. and Mrs. Henry Dain Papers was donated to the Marist College Library by Mr. and Mrs. Henry Dain in 2003.
Restrictions to Access
There are no restrictions on this collection
Historical Note
In September 1962, the Consolidated Edison Company announced plans to build a pumped storage facility, the largest of its kind in the world, at Storm King Mountain near Cornwall, New York. The initial application for license to construct the plant was filed with the Federal Power Commission in January 1963. On November 8, 1963, a small group of concerned citizens met at the home of Carl Carmer and formed the Scenic Hudson Preservation Conference to fight the pumped storage project on the grounds that it posed a threat to the Cornwall water supply and Hudson River fisheries as well as to scenic and historic Storm King Mountain. The case lasted for 17 years. In a negotiated settlement in December 1980, Consolidated Edison agreed to drop the plan for the Storm King facility. In the meantime, Scenic Hudson emerged at the forefront of the environmental movement. Over the past thirty-five years, Scenic Hudson, Inc. has safeguarded over 18,000 acres of irreplaceable landscapes, protected productive farmland, reclaimed and transformed neglected industrial waterfront sites, and purchased strategic properties to revive community centers.
Carl Carmer, author of The Hudson River and other historic works, became honorary chairman and Leo O. Rothchild was named chairman. Rothchild served until 1968 and was succeeded by Alexander Saunders. Initially, the members, working in their own homes or borrowed office space, contacted friends, prominent citizens, politicians, and other organizations for financial support, letter writing campaigns, and legal intervention.
The organizations grew rapidly. Contributions were channeled through the Natural Area Council until Scenic Hudson was incorporated in 1974. Rod Vandivert became the executive director in the mid-1960s. An office was set up in New York City, but the location changed several times during Storm King case and there were a number of office managers during that period. Professional fundraisers and public relations firms were employed in later years.
Aided by other organizations and individuals, the group conducted an intensive campaign to educate the public and to deter Consolidated Edison by legal means. The records, which document the organization’s activities, include publicity materials, copies of legal documents submitted by Scenic Hudson and others, and transcripts of hearings before Congressional sub-committees and the Federal Power Commission. The case lasted for 17 years. In a negotiated settlement in December 1980, Consolidated Edison agreed to drop the plan for the Storm King facility.
The lengthy and controversial case set important precedents in environmental law and is generally credited with spawning the modern environmental movement. Scenic Hudson, Inc. continues to serve as an environmental watchdog in the Hudson Valley.
Related Collections
Collection Overview
The Mr. and Mrs. Henry Dian Papers contains documents and clippings related to the Hudson River Environmental Society, underground transmission lines, and the proposed Cornwall Storage Pump. Legal documents include testimonies, statements, orders, and briefs. The Dains collected clippings from various newspapers collected in a scrapbook, as well as loose.
Arrangement of the Collection
These records are organized into four series: 1.Legal Documents 2. Correspondence 3.Printed Materials 4.Oversized Materials
Series are arranged either alphabetically, chronologically, or by object.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- 1. Legal Documents, 0.12 Linear Feet; Box: 1; Folders: 1-11
  Series contains testimony, statements, briefs, etc. related to environmental issues in the Hudson River Valley.
  Alphabetical
  - Amendment to Application for License - Cornwall (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Application for Re-Hearing - Underground Transmission Lines (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Oral Argument (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Order Granting Intervention (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Overhead and Underground Transmission Lines Hearings (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Petition of Phillipstown Citizens Association (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Presiding Examiner’s Ruling on Requests for Extensions of Time (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Reply Brief (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Report of Hearing (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Statements (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Testimony: Downey, Jeremiah R. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- 2. Correspondence, 1964-1967; 2; 0.01 Linear Feet; Box: 1; Folders: 12-13
  Series contains communication about environmental issues in the Hudson River Valley.
  Chronological
  - Correspondence, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence (large) (Box 1, Folder 13)
- 3. Printed Materials, 1964-1966; 3; 0.11 Linear Feet; Box: 1; Folders: 14-19
  Series contains newspaper clippings, pamphlets, and maps.
  - Clippings 1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Clippings (large), 1967 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Maps (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 19)
- 4. Oversized Materials, 4; 0.2 Linear Feet; Box: 2; Folders: 20-21
  This series contains a large map and scrapbook.
  By object
  - West Point Map (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Scrapbook (Box 2, Folder 21)